# RIHAD VARIAWA

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

#### **Data Analytic**

Probability & Statistics (t-tests, ANOVA), variable reduction (PCA), Segmentation/clustering techniques, Predictive modeling: e.g. logistic regression, linear regression, Time series analysis: e.g. ARIMA Advanced Machine learning algorithms & processes Wealth of experience with applying advanced analytics to a variety of business situations

Decision making ability to turn analytic thinking into production code so it can be embedded in systems that deliver insights or action

Data storage and analysis tools: e.g. SQL, Hadoop, Map Reduce & Spark

Strong understanding of financial metrics & ability to leverage decisions using financials

Confortable 'working virtually' with teammates & customers around the world

Demonstrated success as a problem solver, resultoriented and self-starter

### **Programming Languages**

Python; Scikit-Learn, TensorFlow, Keras

R

SQL

Solidity

C++

JavaScript (D3.js), HTML & CSS

## **Software Applications**

iPython Notebook

**RStudio** 

GitHub and GitKraken

Microsoft Azure

Power BI

MS Office suite

#### **Regulatory Reporting Frameworks**

International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS) International Auditing Standards (IAS) King IV Report on Corporate Governance

#### **Corporate Finance**

Business Strategies Operational Efficiency Forecasting/Budgeting

# **OPEN-SOURCE PROJECTS**

Using Python To Analyse 60 Million US Police Stops Fe "Insights Into Important Issues We Face Today, Racism" •
Loan Application Prediction Challenge

"To Predict Whether A Loan Would Be Approved Or Not" Time Series Analysis Using Python

"Helping Investors Make An Investment In A New Form Of Transportation"

# **EDUCATION**

Postgraduate Diploma Accounting Science (CTA) - 2014 BCompt (Hons) Accounting Science - 2011 BCompt Accounting Science - 2008

## **LINKS**

www.linkedin.com/in/rihad-variawa-7422017b https://2series.github.io https://github.com/2series rihadv021@gmail.com

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Data Scientist - Esource | Analytics

Jan 2017 - Present

- Domain knowledge in financial services such as quantitative finance and risk modeling, discovering the information hidden in vast amounts of data, to enable smarter decisions that will deliver even better products and features
- Created hypotheses about ways to change the renewable energy industry through new uses of data
- Researched and implemented methodologies to measure the impact of renewable energy on the environment
- Aided a healthcare provider improve their clinical trial practices by identifying congestion in diagnostic testing as a key indicator of admissions breaches
- Designed and built a data-driven application for a state of the art Centre of excellence in urban innovation by collecting real-time data from environmental sensors across India and deploying proprietary analytics to find unexpected patterns in air pollution

# Finance Manager - Real Estate Portfolio

Feb 2017 - May 2018

- Through M&A created an asset class portfolio of housing and apartment developments
- Created a machine learning pipeline for real estate investments & built a model that learns from data and was able to predict the median housing prices in any district achieving 89% accuracy
- Delivered timely & accurate quarterly financial and management accounts
- Evaluated risk factors that could adversely affect the assets & implemented procedures to mitigate exposure to risks and disclose risk information to relevant internal & external stakeholders
- Accelerated corporate compliance, operational risks & control processes by monitoring financial obligations with banks and developing credit facilities
- Devised relevant internal controls to ensure the integrity of operations, financial and accounting practices

# **Associate Accountant - Audit Firm**

Feb 2014 - Jan 2017

- Financial service audits of: Asset Fund Managers, Trusts, Property Management Co, SPVs & telecommunication incorporating financial analysis, consolidations & reporting
- Performed a risk based approach to external audits of (private & public) clients in environments providing exposure to risk and compliance management & 2 due diligent reports contributed
- Audited, Monitored and reported by understanding key processes, internal controls, risk identification, risk analysis, responding to risks identified, sound governance & assessed adequate information, communication and monitoring of risk management activities by those charged with governance